STEVEN GILBERT ARCHULETA

6958 Treasure Way Sacramento, California 95831 stevearchuleta@me.com 1-707-734-0108

SUMMARY: The range of my experiences has given me vast scope: an ability to solve problems with limited resources, innovation, flexibility, management skills, and a customer-focused approach toward communication. I love to strategize, organize, and write. Herein, I present you a confident professional with more than 20 years of developing business, research, marketing, education, management, and coding skills. Without hesitation, I can absorb multiple high-level responsibilities while working within the ranks of premium talent. With alacrity, I add MERN full stack software developer to my repertoire and offer you both pleasant personality and my willingness to learn and grow. I hold US and EU (Portuguese) citizenship.

EDUCATIONAL BACKGROUND:

- Graduate School at The National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, Maryland 1998-2000 [FAES] Foundation for the Advancement of Education in the Sciences, Biomedical Research Fellowship, National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, Pathology Lab
- Saint Mary's College of California, Moraga, California 1987-1991
 Bachelor of Arts, Diversified Liberal Arts
- Christian Brothers High School, Sacramento, California, 1986
- Master Gardener, University of Maryland, 2005
- Master Class: Olive Growing, Milling, Branding, University of California at Davis, 2018
- Master Class: Olive Oil Sensory Evaluation, University of California at Davis 2018
- Full-Stack Coding Boot Camp: (24-weeks) University of California at Davis 2019

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE:

Operations / Sales Director: Wolfe Heights Estates, LLC (2018-Present)

Olive Grove: Generated Cost Analysis, Budget, Wholesale Pricing, and Direct Sales of bulk and bottled olive oil from a medium density 10-acre olive orchard. Applied for and earned Organic Certification via the California Council of Organic Farmers. Applied for and earned board approval from the California Olive Oil Council. Entered and won Gold and Silver Awards at the Napa Valley Olive Oil Competition. Generated detailed reporting from Harvest to Milling, Transport to Bottling, Storage to Sales. Certified Completion of the University of California at Davis Olive Center Master Class: Growing, Milling, Marketing. Certified Completion of the University of California at Davis Olive Center Master Class: Olive Oil Sensory Evaluation.

Vineyard: Passed examination for the Private Applicator Certificate through the California Department of Pesticide Regulation. Applied for TTB winery licensing and ABC sales and distribution licensing. Sales, Marketing

Event Center: Hosted Weddings and Events. Wrote and edited a 20-page wedding event contract, Wedding Brochure, Final Walk-Through Form, and Social Media Postings. Toured Clients and 3rd-party Vendors.

Property Management / Inn-keeping Manager / Hospitality (2015-2018):

Stonehurst Place, Atlanta, Georgia, 2017-2018

The Blue Door Group, Mendocino, California, 2015-2016

- Contractually managed high-end top-rated inns: day-to-day operations, staffing, occupancy, digital marketing, reservations, administrative payroll, housekeeping, and also served as liaison between corporate management and third-party sub-contractors.
- Hosted B&B guests and maintained grounds. Prepare high-quality small plate breakfasts.
- Received only 4 and 5 star Trip Adviser reviews

Owner/Operator

The Good Life Market. Randy & Steve's — The New General Store; Ellicott City, Maryland 2005-2013 Owned and operated three unique retail locations:

- Architectural designed and built of a garden-gift retail cottage with a climate controlled barn-style greenhouse (4300 cubic feet; 12x18x20) which earned the unanimous approval of a historic commission).
- Managed all aspects of store operations and logistics, from business planning to the fine details of project management.
- Upgraded The Good Life Market boutique garden store to included a high-end home décor & specialty retail store, women's apparel boutique, grocery and gourmet deli.
- Employed and managed multiple full-time and numerous part-time employees.
- Forged authentic relationships with thousands of loyal, family-oriented customers.

- Won multiple recognitions and awards: 'Best of Baltimore' in "Baltimore Magazine", 2008 & 2010; a feature photo in "Money Magazine" (Time Inc.); the subject of a syndicated comic strip "Close to Home" by John McPherson, an interview and photo shoot by "Southern Living Magazine", "The Washington Post Magazine's" 'Second Glance', Cover photo and feature articles in "Howard Life Magazine", "Howard County Tourism", and other local publications.
- Organized weekly community events: The Fine Dining Supper Club, Sunday Group Meditations, Family-Oriented
 'Movies That Matter', 'Shut Up & Write' Literary Club, 'Soup Night', Tea Ceremonies, and multiple community
 celebrations, including fundraisers for "Smile Train", "Habitat for Humanity", a "Women-2-Women Magazine" launch
 party, Postpartum 'Better Bedrest', Howard County Master Gardeners, Whipps Cemetery, and local public and private
 school charities.
- Increased sales of at least 10% year-over-year revenue from 2005-2009, falling short only in 2010, one year after the recessionary contraction of the American economy. Growth began again, 2011 to 2013.
- Purchased goods (biannual buying trips to AmericasMart Atlanta, Javits Center NYC, Fancy Food Show San Francisco); payroll accuracy, accounts receivable & accounts payable, advertising, merchandising, sales, vendor communications, customer correspondence, community outreach, and charitable donations.

Operation Manager 2000-2002

Celebrate Maryland & Discover America - Columbia, Maryland

Managed operations for six (6) distinct retail stores within three (3) different airports: Baltimore-Washington International, Baltimore Maryland; Ronald Regan International, Washington DC; Orlando International Airport, Orlando Florida. Managed six (6) store managers and six (6) assistant managers. Oversaw and facilitated retail flow of merchandise into and out of three international airports. Responsible for scheduling, establishing sales goals and bonuses, financial reporting, as well as loss prevention and shrinkage. During my tenure, all six (6) stores at all three (3) airports were closed due to company bankruptcy. Editorial Supervisor

Eighteen Inches of Courage — A Journey from the Head to the Heart, The Most Difficult Journey in Life By Soul Coaching® expert Randy Neely, 2011

• Edited this 45,000 word book as well as helped design, publish, and sell over 1000 copies.

<u>Long-Term Substitute Teacher</u> (1995-1996 & 2002 – 2004)

Saint Mary's College High School, Berkeley, California 1995-1996

• Taught Chemistry and Biology to high school students. Assigned final grades.

Howard County School District, Ellicott City, Maryland 2002-2004

- Taught Technology Education to 6th, 7th, and 8th grade students (full time; assigned final grades).
- Taught Basic Drafting to 10th and 11th graders (intermittently)

Biomedical Research Fellow

National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, Maryland 1998-2000

Pathology Section; National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute

- Researched the effects of Matrix Metalloproteinases in inducing structural damage on bioprosthetic heart valves by
 making use of immunohistochemical and fluorescence techniques, particularly in conjunction with laser scanning
 confocal microscopy.
- Schooled in identifying the ultrastructural components of diseased heart valves by using transmission electron microscopy.
- Journal: "Circulation" Publication Titles: 1) Laser Scanning Confocal Microscopy: An Emerging Technique For The Pathologic Evaluation Of Cardiac Devices; 2) Polymeric Scaffold Tissue Engineered Heart Valves: Explant Pathology.

Freelance Author

Comstock's Business Magazine, Sacramento, California 1997

• Authored five (5) feature articles (including one ghost written as the Editor's Letter) that highlighted various large businesses and municipalities throughout the capital region of Sacramento, California. Interviewed proprietors and researched competitive local business markets, met each deadline in a timely fashion.

Assistant Grant Writer

Rosemount, Minnesota 1994

Rosemount School District

• Technology Innovation Challenge Grant

ELIGIBILITY: I am legally eligible to work in the EU (Portuguese Citizenship) and the USA (American Citizenship).